Kannan Kalidasan

TW92JR, London, UK | kannanpoem1984@gmail.com | +44-07552593324 | linkedin.com/in/kannandreams

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Engineering Lead with 18 years of experience in data strategy, data engineering, analytics, and machine learning. Successfully led greenfield data projects in startups and developed cloud-based solutions scaling to petabytes in large organizations. Managed teams of 10+ in both managerial and technical roles. Oversaw entire project lifecycles, including the development of data lakes, data strategy, governance, and quality models.

SKILLS

Data Engineering & Analytics: DBT, Snowflake, Airflow, Fivetran, CDC, Spark, Kafka, Iceberg, Looker, Segment

Cloud Computing: AWS, Lambda, ECS, EKS, Cloud Watch, Athena, S3, EC2, EMR, Kinesis, RDS, BigQuery, Redshift

Software Engineering: Python, SQL, Unix Shell Scripting, Java (Sprint Boot), Rest API, Microservices, React

DevOps: Kubernetes, Docker, Jenkins, Git, Git Actions, CI/CD, Terraform, Grafana, Datadog

Software Engineering: Rest API, Microservices, HTML/CSS

Machine Learning / AI: MLOps, Feast, scikit-learn, Flyte, SageMaker, mlflow, HuggingFace

Domains: Marketing, CRM, Salesforce, Ads, Product Analytics, eCommerce

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Let's Do This, UK | Data Engineering Lead

07/2023 - present

- Led a 4 member engineering team to deliver analytics and LLM based solutions for internal and external users.
- Own Data / ML strategy, roadmaps and drive architectures.
- Collaborate with engineering, data science, product managers to deliver data products.
- Delivered Email Campaign recommendation using NLP and LLM APIs.
- Designed the Unified analytics architecture for customer facing dashboards to support OLTP analytics and OLAP.
- Handling data product vendor management, capacity planning and stackholder collobration.
- Streamlined the incremental ETL data ingestion and dbt transformation process and reduced 30% snowflake cost.
- Established data quality KPI and increased over 85% with Tests integration and reduced source issues significantly.
- Generated \$400k ARR from partnership collaboration with Data Clean Room strategy.
- Delivered Self-serve analytics capabilities for the business users.
- Handled Data governance intiatives like Modern Data Architecture, Snowflake RBAC, GDPR compliance across analytics solutions handling PII data and encryption.
- Guided and Contributed to Platform Guidelines, DataOps and engineering best practices.
- Helping the team's individual growth by improving hiring method, 1:1 discussion & performance review.

Chase, UK | VP, Data Engineering

09/2022 - 07/2023

- Led Nutmeg to Chase data migration project and saving over \$100K in AWS costs with architecture redesign.
- Managed nutmeg data integration service to deliver John Lewis investment product to manage customer portfolio.
- Architect the streaming and batch pipelines, CI/CD process and job orchestration to streamline the data deliverables and enhance overall efficiency.
- Managed the data science platform team to support multi-source ingestion capabilities, streaming pipelines and ML pipelines.

Delivery Hero, Germany | Staff Data Engineer

01/2022 - 08/2022

- Delivered Marketing / Ads metrics to empower the CRM and growth team in improving campaign spending, Attribution model and Customer segmentation.
- Designed a GDPR-compliant data lake strategy with elements like the right to be forgotten, data obfuscation, and stringent data access controls.

 Played a key role across the data tribe by participating in architecture decision reviews, introducing best practices, and contributing to the core framework.

Acceldata, India | Data Science Manager

01/2021 - 11/2021

- Led the 6 member Data science team to deliver MLOps product solution to Fortune 500 enterprise customers.
- Data strategy, roadmap, OKRs and influence executive leadership team.
- Work with Product Owners and PMs to prioritise and orchestrate work between pods and engineers.
- Presented MLOps product with Facebook Data Science Team for feedback and pitch for aquisation.
- Delivered AI features such as asset similarity to reduce data duplication in data lake by 20%, Monitoring services for model performance, data drift and lineage.
- Provided technical leadership to a team fostering a culture of collaboration, innovation, and excellence.
- Delivered MLOps library integrated with MLFlow and design the Model Observability Platform.

Expedia, India | Engineering Manager

11/2018 - 07/2020

- Led the data team of 10 members, including Data Engineers, Software Engineers and SDET.
- Managed the expedia click stream team for product analytics, custom attribution model and data science features.
- Collaborated with various cross functional teams and worked with product, engineering, marketing and finance to deliver data driven solutions for business outcomes.
- Cut data cloud costs by 35% during covid through AWS spot instances, non-prod data pipelines optimisation.
- Established best practices and guidelines for development, deployment, and ensured data reliability support.
- Mentor and improve the technical skills of other team members through peer reviews.
- Continuously improved the company's data engineering practices & maturity with modern tech stacks, inner source
 contributions and trainings.

INDG, Netherlands | Data Architect

09/2017 - 11/2018

- Implemented a AWS serverless architecture solution to improve scalability, efficiency and reduced 40% cloud cost.
- Deployed an AI-based auto-tagging feature to streamline metadata tagging of 3D models and images, reducing
 manual effort by 50% and significantly improving metadata search efficiency.
- Deployed product analytics to understand conversion rates, customer usage, support A/B testing, and gain insights into product features.

Target, India | Lead Machine Learning Engineer

10/2016 - 08/2017

- Developed ML based Estimated Delivery Time Prediction Service, resulting in annual savings of \$20 million and enhancing the overall customer delivery experience.
- Built an in-house ML as a Service Framework featuring common libraries, automated data profiling, model versioning, and MLOps capabilities.

Expedia, India | Senior Data Engineer

06/2014 - 08/2016

- Led the on-premises to cloud data pipeline migration project of handling of petabyte-scale data.
- Guided BI & Analytics team in creating global data platforms for multiple Orbitz brands worldwide.
- Promoted Spark based data pipelines with EMR to reduce processing time and improve SLAs.

Fidelity Investments, India | Tech Lead

06/2011 - 06/2014

• Designed and implemented a data model and ETL that enabled analytics for the asset management department, which improved the speed of insights by 35%.

TCS, India | Senior Software Engineer

12/2009 – 04/2011

EDUCATION

B.TECH, Computer Science & Engineering, Pondicherry University

2002 - 2006

OTHER

Technology blogger https://eggpuffengineer.substack.com/ ADPList.org - Top 50 in Data Science Mentoring Contributing Author, R in Business Intelligence, PACKT